People that have to ask that question by
definition are not principal engineers.
>> This is Ilia Gregoric. He grew to a
distinguished engineer at Shopify, which
is a VP level role. And I asked him what
it took to get there. To be a really
effective principal plus engineer, you
need to have very good dynamic range.
Technically,
>> he turned down a clear path to director
at Google to go back to being an
engineer. This is a path that is vastly
underappreciated and is actually
surprisingly common for a lot of
principal and then higher up roles. and
his best advice might change how you
plan your career.
>> A better way, a more resilient way to
build your career is to optimize for
being the only person as opposed to the
best person.
>> Here's the full conversation.
You mentioned you went to Wateroo and I
I I got to ask the smartest interns that
I ever worked with, they came from MIT,
Caltech and Singha University in China.
But the best interns I ever worked with
all came from Waterlue. And so I I'm
curious, what is it that makes these
Waterlue interns so strong? For me
personally, the most important thing
that uh Waterloo got right and better
than most and I know that more schools
have adopted this pattern, but it's
still not well well understood is their
co-op program. So, what water did really
well is they realized that yes, there is
the academic portion of learning how to
engineer and like what software design
is all about. Uh but then there's the
hands-on and applied part. And instead
of modeling it as hey you're going to
study for 3 years and then you have an
optional kind of intermission style
co-op which is what what most university
operate on right you could take a year
off or something like that to go and
work in industry uh wateroo said you
know what we're going to just do a
rotation where every semester you study
you work you study you work you study
you work you know what that means you
don't have a break in between you're
just constantly iterating through this
loop but what it gives you is um at
least six six shots on goal for trying
things, right? And this actually has
very positive effects on many
dimensions. So, first of all, um it
removes the stigma of trying things,
right? Because uh many of us like we
don't know what what what's going to
stick with us. Kind of coming back to my
earlier point about consulting versus
something else or something else. I had
so many of my peers going through
university where we all started with
some preconceived notion of what we
wanted to do. was like, "Oh, I really
want to go to Wall Street and work
there." And they they try one of the
co-op terms there. And they're like,
"No, actually like this for whatever
reason." Mean like I don't like the city
or I don't like the industry. I didn't
like the people. It like it just didn't
click for whatever reason, right? Same
thing for like medicine or others or
consulting. Um, and that's really
important to discover early. And the
really nice thing is it's a concentrated
it's like it's a threemon sprint you get
to try right and you have permission to
try five more things at least without
the stigma of looking at your resume
saying hey like you you went to a role
for 3 months you don't you went to a
role for 3 months you like are you
really like committed are you like do I
want to hire you it's like no that's my
co-op right like that's that's the whole
point so you could first of all try a
bunch of things and get a kind of a good
range of experiences under your belt um
but also see the kind of the gamut of
like hey here's how a large company
operates here's a smaller company here's
a medium but like which which one
resonates with me more right so it's
industry it's uh the type of work that
you do it's the type of an environment
that you're in and I think that is
really helpful on top of that you
actually get exposure to like engineer
things not learn the hypothetical and
academic of like I know how a big
onotation
expresses this particular algorithm.
It's like I actually had to build the
thing, right? Like and turns out this
didn't work or that particular solution
worked or we had to solve it under these
constraints and the whole big old thing
was an issue because I was like sorting
10 items in an array. Who cares, right?
It's like pragmatic engineering. So
I think that is key. um that is still a
superpower of Wateroo and I wish more
universities like it's an open secret
and I wish more people would copy it
because it's such a lever for success
for people that go through that program.
>> After you went through all of those
iterations and all the co-op loops, I
understand that you started your own
company um which became Post Rank that
was then acquired by Google. And I'm
curious the story behind you choosing to
found a company right after graduating
from Waterlue.
>> I graduated from Waterlue and as most
students um I didn't know know what to
do. Um I wasn't ready to to commit. Um
so my escape uh which is which was a
wellrun track for many is I'll go to
grad school. So I I applied and then got
into University of Toronto actually. And
during that summer in between um I had a
couple of project ideas that I wanted to
get off the ground. So I I had a
particular itch that I wanted to scratch
and the itch was if you think back to uh
how Google was founded the key insight
if you simplify it and boil it down that
like Larry and Sergey had back in 1997
is hey um we could treat the link crap
of the internet effectively as a
feedback loop on what is good content.
So if you and I create pages and we link
to each other, that's a mutual signal of
both directions that there's something
there, right? So disconnected pages are
not worth much. But in effect, it's kind
of a social currency. Links are a social
currency. Right? Now, fast forward to
2010, 2011 when I'm sitting there, the
web 2 revolution has already happened or
like well underway. You now all of a
sudden have dynamic content on the web,
not static links, not static web pages,
but we have comments on blogs, right?
Blogs became a thing. Comments became a
common thing. So my observation was,
hey, if a conversation is happening on
Reddit about an interview that Ryan has
recorded like that means there's
something there. I don't I can't
qualitatively say whether it's good or
bad. I just know that people are talking
about it and that a signal. So what if
you built a system that went out and
aggregated all of these interactions and
then built a better version of page rank
effectively right links becomes one
input but you know thumbs up and number
of conversations and number of likes and
all of these things become additional
inputs and that was post post rank right
it's it's kind of embedded in the name
it's it's a was an algorithm for ranking
posts based on social engagement kind of
a child of the web 2 era still remember
the day it was like July 8th when I
released And then I didn't sleep for 3
days because the servers were melting
down. Not strictly because it was like
such huge demand although there was. It
was also because my code was terrible.
So it's kind of like brute force just
throw more servers at the problem and
then eventually you know optimize it out
over the next couple of weeks to to get
it back to a manageable set. So that
becomes kind of this nucleus of hey
there's a there's a feature there right
and it got um it got good publicity uh
which then turned into conversation hey
is there a product here so I remember
the juncture points somewhere late in
May we're kind of in the middle of all
these conversations with investors
um kind of unanticipated fork in the
path right and I'm thinking what what do
I do like I'm uncertain are we going to
be able to close around can I do this
because in a couple of weeks I'm
supposed to start my my grad work and
I'm looking at that syllabus. I'm like
what are the courses I'm most interested
in and I go through the list and it was
like the the ones that immediately stood
out to me about like entpreneurship
and like how to do a company. I'm like
wait a second. So, I could go and learn
about this stuff academically and read
books or I can like I'm literally having
the conversations right now with the
investors like I or I could just like go
and like I I can read those books on my
own time and I go I can go and try it
which uh led me to reaching out to my
adviser and basically asking hey can I
take a a year time out you know I was
planning to do this this year but how
about I start next year and hemmed in
hot and said okay I understand and you
know come back to me in 6 months. Um to
close that story, we did end up closing
the round and that became postrank the
company and uh I never did get to finish
my uh so-called graduate degree.
>> So in the process of building this
company, I know eventually it was
acquired by Google, but I'm really
curious because I feel like a lot of
acquisition conversations are behind the
scenes hush hush. Um what does that kind
of conversation look like like when they
reach out for an acquisition? And maybe
you can tell that story.
It's a lot less stressful than you make
it sound to be. I remember we were
actually
we were building the product that I was
describing and uh we were presenting at
one of the conferences in the Bay Area
and you know we got off stage and uh
Phil Moody who was one who was the uh
kind of lead PM on Google Analytics kind
of walked up to us and like hey this
this is cool uh do you want to have a
chat? And I remember taking a train from
San Francisco to Mountain View later
that day, sitting in the conference room
and him basically interrogating us about
what is it that you build and then um
ending the conversation with, hey, maybe
we should do something together. It's
like, okay, well, tell me more, right?
Um that's a that's a blank check for
follow-up conversation. Um so it it was
it was very friendly. There's there's
nothing uh kind of uh more to it than
that. And then uh what we learned uh
after is this is right in the time span
when Google and Facebook were uh like at
war in terms of drawing the battle lines
for social. Uh this is when Google woke
up to the fact that Facebook is on a
runaway trajectory and um all hands on
deck. Google need. This is when Google
starts working on Google+.
Uh which of course has since been
sunset. But it became this catalyze
catalyzer with the Google for hey we we
need an answer and they were looking for
all the help that they could get and all
the experience that they could acquire
to speedrun this whole thing. Um and we
became that catalyst for Google
Analytics because what they saw in us is
like they frankly they did not care for
the uh
PR product that we were building. what
they cared about was uh the experience
and some of the infrastructure that we
we've accumulated that we could bring in
to fast run and fasttrack this whole
thing to say hey if I'm using Google
Analytics I can get really good insights
on how my social engagement is going and
I can figure out how Google+ is helping
me and all the rest um so that became
the kind of the mutual point of win-win
situation um that led us uh joining
forces with Google Analytics
>> in being brought in as an acquisition
How do they determine leveling or
compensation or any of that stuff?
>> Google as many other tech companies run
the same process. It's usually kind of
accelerated batch model, right? Where
you bring in the whole team and and you
kind of do a a wholesale evaluation, but
otherwise um everyone on our team went
through the panel through the full panel
uh myself included. Uh so that that was
that was the bar and really the exercise
for them was to vet the quality of the
team and then to figure out where kind
of on the leveling uh do all the
engineers stuck up. I see. Okay. So it's
it is just a normal interview process.
What about in the case though cuz you're
bringing in company and assets and
stuff. Is that just like a giant signing
bonus or something or how's that? it it
depends on the company that that you
know and then the deal of course so
there there's multiple layers to it
exactly as you said right there's the
like there's the IP there's the
customers uh there's the people and you
can treat those as kind of distinct
conversations right so as so far as
negotiation is concerned um are you
acquiring the product what are you going
to do with the customers right um is
there IP there are you going to use the
technology um many like there's the aqua
hire acquisition where you're
effectively acquiring the team you're
cool thing you built, but that's not the
thing I need you to be building. Let's
just put that on the shelf and let's
just focus on like rebuilding the thing
um in our infrastructure. Um post rank
was closer to that. It was not a full
kind of aqua hire because they brought
in and they used the IP, but for all
intents and purposes, the thing that we
built ourselves, we had to rebuild from
scratch with the Google Analytics
because you're just operating at a
completely different order of magnitude,
right? And it was an amazing trial by
fire if anything for our engineering
team because we went from managing tens
of thousands of analytics accounts and
granted yes we were crawling the web at
a fairly large scale to operating in a
service that was literally executing on
half more than half the internet right
so like to to make a modification to a
data pipeline I remember the
conversations fondly um like sitting
with our SR team and they're like okay
well you're going to at this bit field
right here. That's going to be this
number of exabytes of data. I'm like,
"Oh my god,
okay. Uh, let me think about this more
carefully, right?" Because before that
was not even a a conversation point for
me and and my team. So
um a lot of it was about the talent and
bring making ensuring that they're
bringing in the right folks with the
right experience and u that they're
capable of kind of hitting the ground
running and and working with with the
rest of the Google Analytics team.
>> So I want to get into your career at
Google and it sounds like you were
placed initially in Google Analytics.
I'm curious what the leveling was and
the role. Were you a manager because you
mentioned your you brought your team
with you. Um so I was founder and CTO of
Postrank and I joined as an engineering
manager um because effectively that's
what my my role was um at Google and I
was very invested in making sure that we
build the right thing the right way and
kind of manifest the vision of why we
started this damn company to begin with
because I strongly believed in like I
want to help publishers understand that
was still like me scratching my own itch
of like I'm going to make Google anal
analytics solve my problem. Damn it.
Um and um I think we we succeeded um at
that. It took us about a year to
effectively rebuild our stack and the
team was on a good trajectory and and
that's where I
uh took us to back and looked around for
hey what's the next adventure? um I was
in a really good direction uh within
Google Analytics and I remember um a
conversation with one of our VPs at the
time where uh you know we were having
one of these career sitdowns and he was
like look um you have all the things you
need you're on track for director you
know here are the things that I I could
see I could see you take on and all the
rest and like huh that sounds all
exciting and like and I'm very honored
that like
you think I'm capable of doing this work
but at the same time um I couldn't not
let my curiosity get the better of me
like Google is such an amazing technical
playground that even though that first
year was a pressure cooker of like I
need to get this thing shipped right and
I'm going to work my my butt off to get
it working I also was spending every
free moment of time just like
diving deep into various design
documents and wikis uh Google is an open
culture which is the thing that I loved
about Google And I could approach anyone
and everyone about um any piece of
infrastructure, any product. And I
leveraged that um and I learned a lot
because you know I remember building
Post rank and reading papers that were
published about Bigtable this and Hadoop
that and like trying to figure out how
to replicate some of the magic that
Google had and then I'm reading the
internal design documents and I'm like
oh my god this is three generations
ahead of this paper that I was reading.
This is amazing right? Like I wish the
world knew about this right? And then I
would half the time I would talk to the
engineers. I'm like, "How come we never
published a follow-up on this thing?"
They're like, "We're too busy."
It's not that it's a trade secret. We're
literally too damn busy. Like, you know,
if you find us the time and I was like,
"Huh, well, that's interesting." Like,
wouldn't it benefit the entire world,
the entire like internet if we did more
of this? um which led me down some
interesting conversations and I
discovered this group within Google
which was called make the web fast which
is basically a skunk course project
started by uh Sergey
um around well how can we make the
internet fast u and it's a very kind of
self-reerential self-motivating thing um
that there's very direct evidence that
the faster the internet is the faster
users brow the browse the web the more
they use Google so So it's a mutually
beneficial relationship, right? So
within that group, we had all kinds of
fun projects. We literally built radio
towers trying to figure out how to build
more effective cellular networks. Uh you
know, dug trenches built built towers.
Uh we worked on TCP IP and trying to
figure out how to reduce congestion. Uh
we worked at optimizing proxies for hey,
turns out that most humans write
terrible websites. Could we just like
optimize it out kind of dynamically as a
web server plugin to um hold on a second
when we say make the internet fast? What
does that even mean? Like we know it
when we see it and when we feel it, but
if you had to put a number on it, how do
you express that? Right? So if you if
you walk the full dynamic range of those
questions, you like it's it's an just
absolutely amazing laboratory of like
experiments to run. And I was really
fascinated about about that. And I
remember at that at that point in time I
I I realized that I had I had an
opportunity to cash in some chips and I
could say look um I I see a path towards
kind of career growth as a director in
this and that and that that would be a
great achievement. On the other hand, I
could take a step back. I could take
this lateral step and go and work as an
IC in this field. I'm actually not quite
even sure how I'm going to contribute. I
just know that this is a really cool
area that I'm passionate about and I'll
hopefully probably find something useful
that I can do there. Um, but that would
definitely take me off the career track,
right? I remember that conversation. It
was like, well, you know, if uh IC bar
at Google is actually really high, so if
anything, you're going to be downleveled
likely
um and you're going to reset your track.
I was like, okay, I think that's a trade
worth having because I get to control my
time. I get to work with people I look
up to and I get to work in a particular
on a domain that I think is just
absolutely fascinating. So, I made that
pivot and in retrospect it was an
amazing right decision for me because um
it allowed me to kind of flex my
curiosity and technical muscle in a
completely different direction. you
turned down this more clear-cut director
path which would be the clear-cut growth
path for career um to optimize for other
things which was sounds like intrinsic
motivation in the work curiosity and
also sounds like maybe you got some time
back is that the math you were doing in
your head and making that choice
>> exactly that it was and there was a lot
of uncertainty in that process but um
this kind of a a repeating arc through
my career where as a manager your time
is managed by others,
right? Like you you are in the service
of others and I wanted to uh shift gears
and and go into a mode where I have more
self-direction and go pursue some like
interesting research or uh projects that
like where I can apply my own skill set
in a unique way. So later I saw that you
switched back to management and you're
director of uh developer relations at
Google. So what was the rationale then
switching back given what you just said?
Yeah. So, I've seesawed um a number of
times through IC to manager and I think
this is a path that is vastly
underappreciated and is actually
surprisingly common uh for a lot of like
high performing
um IC's and like you'll find in in
principle and then higher up roles and
the observation is um I think as a tour
of duty uh when I'm when I'm doing
management um to be a really effective
like principle plus engineer you need to
have very good dynamic range technically
right and you can you can work well at a
low level of the stack you can also zoom
out and look at the business
requirements kind of deeply understand
what's actually necessary where can you
relax constraints uh where can you where
you need to hold hold the line and all
the rest and once you get attached to
certain projects like some projects you
can execute and you call it done you're
like a great I solved that problem right
but many problems that are handed to you
they they become they come as nebulous
statements that then evolve into huh
this is actually like a team's worth of
effort like now that we've understood
the shape of this problem and uh what
often happens is you you kind of you see
this pattern of um some individual doing
the trailblazing work path finding where
where we need to climb and then they
find themselves okay now I need to
recruit a team of people to help me
actually build the thing like I know how
to get to the top of that hill with a
machete. But now we need to build a
highway, right? And to build a highway,
I need a team. Okay, well, let me go
find a team. Before you know it, you're
kind of you're you're a TL,
right? And you're exercising your soft
power to help direct people and all the
rest. It's not a far stretch to switch
to a manager, right? Because like, well,
now you're doing performance management
as well, plus a few other tricks. But
often times, you'll find kind of
yourself um managing or being
responsible for the direction of a
broader team. And before you know it,
like I think it's a natural transition
to say, well, okay, fine. I'm going to
like manage this domain. I'm going to
manage this as a product team. I'm going
to manage this like the growth of the
individuals and the rest. And that's
completely fine. That's what happened to
me with developer relations. Um, when
you think back to the kind of the set of
problems that I that I shared with you,
um, I ended up gravitating towards the
question of how do you measure
performance?
And I found myself doing a lot of web
standards work. I got engaged with W3C
and ITF and and trying to figure out hey
what kind of metrics can we define in
browsers such that we all have a common
ground truth for how to measure
performance and that was great a lot of
that and that was my kind of IC
contributor role um then you get those
metrics into browser and then the
problem becomes great how do I get
community or ecosystem adoption on this
thing well I need to go tell people and
I need to convince them to adopt it
right uh and integrate it Well, now I
need to go talk to all of the analytics
vendors. Uh, let me go talk to all the
open source projects, right? That
problem does not scale with one human.
Like, you really need help of other
humans. This is where the go to market
and the kind of developer relations part
came in. And I quickly realized that
like it would be really helpful to have
a team of people that can focus on this
thing. And this is a thing we deeply
care about. We want to accelerate the
adoption of these things. It's kind of
my my
um model based on prior experience was
look if we just leave this ecosystem be
as it is in 3 to 5 years time we will
probably see the adoption that we want
but I'm not happy with 3 to 5 years like
my question is how can I compress it
into one to two years ideally one year
or less right and for that to happen we
need to inject we need to inject energy
into the system that energy is a team of
people great fine let me switch to the
my manager role. I'm going to go recruit
people and I'm going to like put my
organizer hat on and we're going to go
and execute this problem.
>> So when you say tour of duty, it's this
starting as an IC doing pathf finding
and then becoming a manager potentially
is all in service of a mission or a
problem like you you see some problem
maybe em is the best way to solve that
problem maybe IC is but it's really all
about the problem.
>> Exactly. Exactly. And it's kind of like
your relationship and your commitment to
the problem, right? Because not every
problem has to become your mission. Um
I'm often engaged in projects where I'm
participating. I'm actively contributing
and then I say, "Look guys, you're
you're well on the way. Like you have
the right vector. Go execute. You have
everything you need. Like you don't need
me here." And in fact, that's my kind of
measure of success as a as a principal
engineer often times, right? I don't if
the team is dependent on me pro that
means that I'm probably doing something
wrong because my job is to uplevel the
team and make sure that they can deliver
this thing self-sufficiently. So if you
know the uh the Homer Simpson meme where
he like disappears into the bushes.
>> Yeah.
>> Right. Like it's like kind of like that
like if I can pull that off successfully
on a project and the team continues
executing in the right direction with a
good velocity like that's success for me
oftent times. Now, occasionally I
stumble into a problem where I'm like
either I'm like just it's in my bones
and I feel like I need to be like I want
to own that problem and see it to it
logical conclusion. um or I have some
unique position or leverage in it where
like yes I'm the right person to take on
the broader responsibility and kind of
execution of the team to see it through
completion and it's a judgment call for
which you know when you pull that off
and when you say okay this is going to
be my tour of duty like my job is over
the next I know that I'm committing for
the next two years or something to like
really run this thing own this ship and
that's my responsibility and you know
what at the end of it I'm gonna do the
same thing I did before. I'm gonna like
my success I have I need a succession
plan and my succession plan is either we
solve the problem and it's done or I've
set it on a trajectory where I can
successfully pull back and focus on the
next thing and to focus on next thing.
I'm going to become an IC again and go
find the next thing to solve. I know
later the story continues with you went
to Shopify, you became an IC and you
went from a principal engineer to a
distinguished engineer. I'm curious what
is the tour of duty there that got you
promoted? One of the I think
underappreciated or misunderstood
aspects of being a principal engineer is
when people ask
what what does what do you do like you
know g give me give me a job description
because I want to become a principal
engineer like what are the boxes I need
to tick and the answer is actually
embedded in the question because people
that have to ask that question by
definition are not principal engineers
right because the problems become
ambiguous enough at that level where you
kind of have to figure it out yourself.
Like my expectation for I I mentor a lot
of uh principal engineers that come into
Shopify. Uh my expectation for someone
coming in that level is look uh you're
basically to use an analogy here, you're
going to be dropped parachuted into
foreign terrain. You're on a
reconnaissance reconnaissance mission
and within the first seven days you
should figure out the lay of the land
and figure out where the problems are.
Build alliances with your directors,
VPs, whoever it needs to be. figure out
what their problems are and then kind of
understand the situation and figure out
where you can apply your particular
skill set to help them. Right? I don't
have a prescription for you. Like it it
is your agency. It is your problem to
figure this out. And that requires a
particular kind of skill set and a
toolkit that you have to develop to
figure that out, right? Because there's
a lot of ambiguity in that. um going to
a level above that uh kind of as a
distinguished engineer it's even more
amorphous in many ways there isn't any
shared definition right but I the way I
think about it is uh proof of the
dynamic range of the problems that you
can solve so and then dynamic range kind
of goes in a couple of different
directions one is technically u so are
you able to have you shown a repeatable
record of being able to oper operate
kind of at all layers of the stack. If
you're engaged with the team, are you
able to kind of go all the way down to
the bare metal and understand what are
the constraints, what are the problems
kind of from ground truth, reconstruct
the problem. At the same time, are you
able to operate with the business
requirements, you know, with your VP and
product counterparts to actually
understand what's in their head, how it
manifests in code and translate that
into actionable change and like deliver
the right product. That's the technical
aspect of it. Um but then there's also
the uh the execution model uh kind of in
the middle where you have to be able to
flex. Uh there are different types of
projects that you get parachuted into.
Some projects are uh working at the
frontier of knowledge or product space
where there's like just fog of war. You
don't know what you don't know. And you
have to be working kind of startup mode
of look, we're going to fire. We're
going to see where it lands. Then we're
going to aim and we're going to fire
again. And we're going to do that really
rapidly, really fast, as quickly as we
can, so we can figure out where the hell
we are and then we'll figure out what
we're going to build, right? That
requires a particular skill set. On the
other hand, you can be parachuted into
kind of a slower moving pace pace layer
of the company where it's like, okay
guys, we have this uh platform API
problem, you know, we have a just using
like a random example, right? Um, and
it's really important that we think
through how we design this API because
it will have second and third order
repercussions like years down the road
for our partner ecosystem and all the
rest. So, we need to engage our slow
thinking brain to really understand how
this change at this layer will manifest
its way through all the others, right?
And that's a very different mode of
engagement. That's like that's much more
in a way academic. But you also need to
be able to take all of that divergent
thinking and converge the problem to
like here here's the actual
recommendation, right? So it really
becomes the demonstration of your
toolkit of being able to execute across
all of those domains because when you
talk to like the expectation for a
distinguished engineer is kind of
similar to a VP like it is a VP
equivalent role, right? Like write me a
description for a VP.
The job of a VP is to solve every
problem that lands on their plate,
right? It's like and by definition all
the easy problems have been solved
before like at layers below them so they
only get the hard problems with
incomplete information or imperfect
decisions. So, uh, show me the volume
and show me the versatility of your
toolkit.
That gives me confidence that I could
parachute you into like I can give you
this weird shaped problem next and with
reasonable success you'll be able to
navigate yourself out of it. One thing
that I I share often with u folks that I
coach and work with is I I I have this
belief that a better way a more
resilient way to build your career is to
optimize for being the only person as
opposed to the best person. So
what does that actually mean? There
there are two different paths that you
could take. You could say, look, I'm
gonna pick a particular domain and I'm
going to be the best person that will
know the most about a particular thing.
So I'm going to like take security as an
example, right? I'm going to learn
everything there is to know and that's
going to be my life life calling. And
that's great. There's absolutely nothing
wrong with that. Um you you can optimize
for that. My personal philosophy is um
that is one way to success but it is not
the most resilient way to success. Uh
because what if you pick the wrong
field? What if the world changes under
you? What if um your particular company
does not need that particular skill set?
Be the only to me is is about building a
talent stack or a portfolio of skills
that you can juggle and be effective.
And I think this is actually um reflects
back in the dynamic range conversation
that we were just having, right? Were
you able to say look uh and maybe this
is actually me justifying my own career
track because when I look back on my
career, I could say like look, I was a
mediocre designer. I was a mediocre um
salesperson.
I was okay at support, but like come on.
Like that that's not my life calling
either. But you know what I did really
well? I combine all of those things into
a unique toolkit that other people could
not do. Like I could look at a problem
and I could say, "Yeah, I could sling
together website. I know Photoshop well
enough and I know how to host it and I
know how to secure it and I can stand
all that up for you in, you know, in the
next two days." You don't have to hire a
team for that and I have I have the
dynamic range to do that. Now, if it
turns out that um we now hired a graphic
designer, that's excellent. But great,
I'm just going to take that particular
skill set out of my quiver, hand it over
to them, and I'm going to focus on the
other things, right? And I think
generally uh you can acquire very high
competence like 80 90% uh competence
very quickly in a domain. You can get to
80% in a matter of days to weeks and
especially now with the tools that we
have access to with LLMs and all the
rest like the ability to acquire context
is uh just amazing.
you can spend the next year to get
yourself to 90%.
And now if you optimize for that, you
have resilience because I'm able to
converse
with our marketing team because you know
what? I took the time like I I literally
remember going on Amazon and I bought
15 books on marketing and I spent a week
nothing but reading marketing books so I
could understand the lexicon, the jargon
and and speak the right words when I
talk to marketing teams.
I'm also adept enough at uh working with
our PR teams because like I've written a
lot, right? And I've practiced that
muscle. I'm also an engineer. So I now
I'm able to bridge. So oftent times when
I find myself in conversations at
Shopify or elsewhere, I'm the translator
between all of these different parts of
the company and organs of the body where
I'm able to kind of synthesize that
information and bring it together. And
that gives me a lot of versatility,
right? It doesn't mean that I'm the
smartest person in in the room.
Oftenimes it's far from the uh from the
truth. I'm often the most senior person,
but rarely am I the most knowledgeable.
And that's actually very important
because part of my skill set is to
figure out who are the most
knowledgeable people and figure out how
to leverage them in the most effective
way. Right? My contribution is I
understand kind of the fundamentals of
the platform and what you can do with um
our APIs or our platform. I understand
the business requirements. There's a
very messy middle in the middle of how
you actually implement the solution with
a number of variants.
That's not my responsibility. My
responsibility is to help the people
that know the most about that messy
middle through that decision space. And
I have a toolkit to help them facilitate
that.
But it's not it doesn't mean that you
know the most senior person in the room
knows all the answers which I think is a
mistake that a lot of engineers make
when they think about principal
engineers like oh if you're a principal
you know everything there is to know
about the web platform. It's like well
not really right like what I've learned
is a lot of pattern matching. I've
learned how to find answers. I know
where to find answers and I know how to
navigate out of tricky situations. But
it doesn't mean that I know every API
and every quirk. Now, some people do
because that's what they make their life
calling. And that's I think that that's
perfectly fine. But as a general
strategy, I think it's not as resilient.
Antifragile career is where you have a
set of these capabilities where you can
just swap out any given moment and say,
"Okay, well, I guess I'm solving a go to
market problem right now, so let me pull
out my
other quiver of capabilities."
>> I see. So when you say don't be the
best, be the only, you're saying that
generalists have an advantage because
they can put together a bunch of skill
sets, get most of the way there, and be
the only because the intersection of all
those skill sets is more special and
more resilient because you have such a
wide toolbox. Is that right?
>> Yeah. This is this is literally
probability math, right? It's like how
many people if you multiply out the
probabilities of how many people know
this particular have this particular
skill set like you know enough about
databases you know enough about graphics
you know about you do you know enough
about all these other components who is
the person that is the only person that
has sufficient domain expertise and
connective tissue to solve this problem
right so the being the only is about
having a wide range of tools that you
can reach into and say hey I can combine
them in any particular way which is what
makes you versatile and makes you
effective in these kind of ambiguous
situations where you can based on the
situation adapt how you work, right?
Because I can shift gears and say,
"Look, I've I've been a manager before.
I understand what it means to do
performance management. I understand how
to coach people." Um, so I can even if
I'm working as an IC, I can take an
engineer aside and say, "Look, like
here's some feedback or here's some
recommendations here. I know how to
conduct myself. I know what things to
say, what not to say and and help them
along the way, right? It doesn't mean
that I'm exercising that skill all the
time, but I'm able to be parachuted into
situation where I can act as that
temporarily. And that's turned out to be
incredibly helpful. I had one mentor who
did seesaw as well. And he said that
management always appreciates an IC that
understands management because it's much
easier to partner with them.
>> Yes, absolutely. So I would absolutely
encourage um if you're an IC track and
you've never tried management like def
like being a TL is a great learning
wheels um you should definitely try if
it if it suits you to do management as
well but don't assume that it's a
one-way path right you can go back and
forth and there isn't a stigma I think
historically there has been in some
organizations because also we've kind of
painted this picture of hey the path to
success is you grow to be a manager
right but That's not like when I talk to
a lot of managers in like high roles,
directors and all the rest, you know,
after you sit at a bar and and have a
couple of drinks, they're like you
reflect back on what was when were you
happiest in your career? They say, "Huh,
you know, it was a couple years back
before I became an ex because I had like
I was really competent at that thing and
I was loving it, but I was told that in
order for me to like grow quote unquote,
I needed to take on this other thing."
It's like well huh well that's that's an
interesting reflection right and at the
same time they will reflect and say but
I've also learned a lot in this new role
I appreciate what it means to run a team
the complexity the interpersonal
dynamics the performance management and
all the rest and that's an amazing tool
to have in your toolkit great now um
let's set up our organizations in a way
where that is okay for people to transit
between those roles you're not penalized
and let's not as an industry positioned
as some sort of like demotion, right?
Because often times it's like, oh,
you're a manager. You became an IC. What
happened? What do you mean what
happened? Like nothing happened. I just
I I wanted to take on a new challenge.
Like that's not a demotion.
>> When you look over the course of your
career, were there any points where you
have regrets that others could learn
from?
>> Don't let the pressure of your success
stop you from trying. Um, let let me
unpack that a little bit. Uh, I
reflected on this like as as a writer,
as a blogger. I remember like when I
look back, um, and I wonder if you can
if you can relate to this. When I look
back on my early writing, I read it now,
I'm like, oh my god, that is terrible.
What was it? Like, how could I have
published that? That is just flatout
embarrassing. I hope nobody finds this,
right? Or frankly, if I go on GitHub and
look at my own projects, like it is
embarrassing code. But you know what? It
was the limit of my ability at the time
when I did it. And I'm so glad that I
did it, right? Because it was those
milestones like putting that work out
there that gave me the right feedback,
gave me the right encouragement that
then led me to improve. But the
challenge that you run into is as you
level up and as you get like an audience
and an expectation, it's like, well, you
know, Ryan's interviews are really good.
So, in the next one, like I I expected
to be like an out of the park, better
than ever. You keep setting a higher and
higher bar where you start to filter
like, you know, here's a thing I would
have published before, but I'm not sure
if it's up to my standard now. Like, is
it really interesting? Do I have a
unique take on it? Whereas before it was
like, I don't care. like and just a
thought. Here you go. Keep publishing.
Like I struggle with this all the time.
Like keep putting stuff out there
because don't let that expectation
become a gate and filter for the work
that you put out because that feedback
that you get and exposure is like that
that is actually the quintessential
ingredient that you need for growth.
>> Definitely. Definitely. And yes, I can
relate. I think there was uh there's a
year or two where I was writing a
newsletter and every week I'd publish
something and at some point the email
list is growing and it's growing and I
could tell at the beginning when I'm
ideulating what am I going to write this
week a lot more nos coming in my mind I
go oh no this one this topic's not good
I've seen this somewhere
>> yeah it's it's that courage to be wrong
to be disliked to make a mistake right
it's like Ryan I thought you're like or
Ilia like I I thought you were smarter
than that. Like why did you say that
thing? It's like well that's what came
to my mind and like it's fine. I I don't
claim to be an oracle, right? I I have I
have other um expertise and and other
things and this is what I thought at the
time.
>> Definitely. Yeah. And I I also wonder if
that kind of similar thinking as you
grow in your career, I mean it would
take some courage for you to step into a
new area that's completely new to you.
If everyone knows you as distinguished
engineer and very knowledgeable in your
given domain to step into some new area
where you're going to make a lot of
mistakes that that feeling of that
downgrade is is tough for a lot of
people. Yeah, that's where setting the
right expectations with yourself and
others is also very important. Like the
the way you show up to these
conversations makes all the difference,
right? Because I don't show up as hey I
know all the answers. Rather, I show up
as hey guys I'm here to help. I'm just
I'm like really curious and I start
asking why like what are the
fundamentals? Help me understand this.
the way you ask questions becomes very
important because it's very easy to come
across as trying to question all the
things as opposed to being curious right
like there's a subtle difference between
them um am I trying to attack your work
or am I just trying to construct a model
and just setting clear expectations of
that um often times when I begin these
conversations I'm just very open about
guys I don't know what you what you know
right and I need to very rapidly build
my mental model of the space. So I'm
going to ask a lot of dumb questions
like excuse me upfront. I also have my
expertise and I also know some other
things that you don't. um so help me
navigate through this and it becomes a
collaborative exercise right because I
can uh clear roadblocks and do things
that they can't but they can bring all
of the knowledge and this becomes the
symbiotic relationship of that goes back
to how do I leverage the expertise of
people in the room as opposed to trying
to question their work and that takes a
lot of that stigma out of that new
environment um in work but I think
there's uh an even higher filter for
when you're like broadcasting because
there's an expectation and an aura of
like what what you're expected to be
saying, right? And I think it's um some
people do a better job of that than
others in terms of staying true to
their thoughts and and less filtering.
>> Is there a top book that impacted your
career?
>> The first thing that comes to mind and
this is uh this not a book but an author
uh Sir Ken Robinson.
uh he has a series of books um on like
finding your element, creative schools
and the rest. U if nothing else um go
on YouTube and search for Ken Robinson
and watch his TED talks. Uh it is I
think 20 minutes of your time that is
going to be the highest ROI if not today
this week maybe this year. Uh he he's
been an inspiration to me and I think
his messages needs to be continued. uh
unfortunately he passed away but a key
of it is we need to rethink how we think
about education and it actually kind of
circles back to the conversation we're
having about wateroo his messages
stop we need to rethink our education
system from a factoryline model where we
like put people by age into a certain
bin and teach them specific skills like
we all spike in different ways at
different points in our life right like
let's have an environment where people
can choose their own adventure Now that
how do you execute that turns out to be
really hard and he dedicated his life to
trying to figure that out like how do
you reform the educational system but I
think his philosophy is very much kind
of in line and probably informed a lot
of my thinking for hey it is about
creativity you should mix things up. You
should combine skills. uh let's build a
system that actually allows us to like
help kids learn these behaviors better
as opposed to pigeon holing themselves
into like well no you're in grade five
in grade five you're only supposed to
learn this thing thank you very much and
uh like please don't touch advanced math
until you like until you get to grade
six it's like well that's that's
nonsense right like for some kids they
can go all the way to grade eight math
when they're in grade five just to use
one example
>> and then the last question is if you
could go back to yourself at the
beginning of your career and give
yourself some advice knowing everything
you know now what would you say
>> I would come back to the don't be the
best be the only um I I think early in
my career had a lot of fear of
hey I'm I'm mediocre at a lot of things
like I I see my friends I would look up
to my friends who are really good at
design and I' like oh I wish I could do
that right or I look to my other friends
who are just better engineers like I
wish I could that could do that but the
thing that I had was ability to
negotiate across all those themes and
that's uncomfortable because I wasn't
sure if that would pan out and it turns
out that it did um and then the other
thing is exactly as we were just
discussed don't like don't don't filter
be be braver about this stuff um it's
it's kind of ironic that later in my
career I part of like my 9 to five
effectively became public speaking.
Going through high school, I was deathly
afraid of public speaking.
I would run away from class to avoid it.
Right? Like I I vividly remember those
stories. And then it dawned on me later
when I was doing post rank that hey h
why is it that I was even through
university like I had cold sweats
standing out in front of a class trying
to explain the thing uh but I was
totally adept and fine when I was
pitching uh my product to an audience
and the difference is in one hand I I
was trying to describe a thing that you
know I didn't have any particular
investment in it was a test of my
knowledge versus here's a thing I'm
passionate about and I want to like
enact change in the ecosystem to move it
to some new direction. So that turned
out to make all the difference for me.
And uh maybe that's the key thing like
if you told me uh early in my college
career that my future holds public
speaking, I would I don't know what I
would do. I would say that you're crazy.
>> I see. So to be more brave, chase your
passions.
>> Yeah. And it's also very different when
you're chasing your passion. Kind of a a
lot of things flip in in how you engage
um as opposed to being told to stand up
and you know and rehearse a skit. 100%.
Awesome. Well, thank you so much for
your time, Ilia. I'm really excited to
share this one with everyone. Is there
anything you want to say to the audience
before we end the the recording?
>> I think we covered a lot of ground. Um,
I hope some of it is useful and um, you
can find me on on the internets and
please feel feel free to reach out and
and have a chat.
>> Awesome. I'll put that in the show
notes. All right. Thank you.
>> Thanks, Ryan. Appreciate it.
>> Thanks for listening to the podcast. I
don't sell anything or do sponsorships,
but if you want to help out with the
podcast, you can support by engaging
with the content on YouTube or on
Spotify. If you want to drop a review,
that'll be super helpful. And if there's
any guests that you want to bring on to,
please let me know. I feel like sourcing
very senior IC's, there's no wellstudied
list out there on Google that I can just
search this up. So, if there's someone
in your org or at your company who you
really look up to and you want to hear
their career story, let me know and I'll
reach out to